Devastating floods are becoming more and more common around the world.
毁灭性的洪水在世界各地变得越来越普遍。
The warming climate is leading to heavier rainfall, but could the way that cities are growing be making things worse?
气候变暖导致降雨量增加，但城市的发展方式是否会让情况变得更糟？
Could we design cities in a different way to reduce the risk of flooding?
我们能否以不同的方式设计城市来降低洪水风险？
As cities expand, and more and more land is underneath concrete or paving, less water is absorbed and more needs to be channelled away by storm drains and sewerage systems.
随着城市的扩张，越来越多的土地被混凝土或铺砌路面覆盖，吸收的水分减少，更多的水需要通过暴雨排水沟和下水道系统疏导。
As they become overwhelmed by the volume of water, the risk of flash flooding increases.
当它们被大量的水淹没时，暴洪的风险就会增加。
Could it be that we've been taking the wrong approach?
会不会是我们采用了错误的方法？
Chinese landscape architect Yu Kongjian certainly thinks so.
中国景观设计师俞孔坚确实这么认为。
In 2013, he proposed the concept of 'sponge cities', which are designed to soak up water – like a sponge – reducing the risk of sudden floods.
2013年，他提出了"海绵城市"的概念，旨在像海绵一样吸收水分，降低突发洪水的风险。
Natural solutions are encouraged, using riverside parks and ponds to absorb floodwater.
鼓励采用自然解决方案，利用河滨公园和池塘吸收洪水。
Approaches inspired by this have been taken by cities across the world.
世界各地的城市都采用了受此启发的方案。
Auckland, in New Zealand, was named the spongiest city in one study.
新西兰的奥克兰在一项研究中被评为最"海绵"的城市。
It has replaced the concrete culverts around the Oakley creek stream with green banks and connected parks.
它用绿色河岸和相连的公园取代了奥克利溪流周围的混凝土涵洞。
This has reduced flooding in the nearby residential areas as well as the amount of associated contamination which used to be washed into the sea.
这减少了附近居民区的洪水，也减少了过去会被冲入大海相关污染物的数量。
Auckland has taken a natural approach, but a much more high-tech method can be seen in Amsterdam.
奥克兰采用了自然的方法，但在阿姆斯特丹可以看到一种更高科技的方法。
The Dutch city has installed blue-green roofs on a number of buildings.
这座荷兰城市在许多建筑上安装了蓝绿屋顶。
These roofs have a layer of plants on the outside, and then layers underneath which collect and store rainwater.
这些屋顶外部有一层植物，植物下面的一些层（比如过滤层、储水层、根阻层和防水膜）被用来收集和储存雨水。
This water can be used by people in the building below to water plants or flush toilets.
这些水可以被楼下的居民用来浇灌植物或冲厕所。
Sophisticated software can even tell the roofs to release water ahead of upcoming storms to maximise the system's ability to soak up rainwater.
复杂巧妙的软件甚至可以在即将到来的风暴前指示屋顶释放水，以最大化系统吸收雨水的能力。
It can even identify which areas of the city are at most risk and tailor the response accordingly.
它甚至可以识别城市中哪些区域风险最高，并相应调整应对措施。
Yu Kongjian describes the sponge city approach as using Tai Chi with nature instead of boxing.
俞孔坚将海绵城市的方法描述为与自然打太极而不是拳击。
Questions have been raised as to whether a natural approach is sufficient when faced with increased rain fall globally.
面对全球降雨量增加的情况，自然方法是否足够，人们提出了质疑。
What remains to be seen is whether increased scale and combination with modern technology can help natural methods save many more people from flooding.
还有待观察的是，扩大规模并与现代技术相结合，能否帮助自然方法拯救更多人免受洪水之害。